Finding Aid for Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam records and sound recordings, 1965-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam records and sound recordings
1965-1966
Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam (1965: Ann Arbor, Mich.)
851510 Bimu C8 2
An international conference on Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam held at the University of Michigan, Sept. 14-18, 1965. Correspondence, minutes, clippings, printed materials, and sound recordings.
0.5 linear feet
15 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes
38.8 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of these records and tapes came from Rev. J. Edgar Edwards of Guild House (donor no. 4537 ) in 1967. A smaller portion came from Rev. Daniel Burke of Canterbury House (donor no. 4420 ) in 1966.
The record group is open to research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The International Conference on Alternative Perspectives on Viet Nam brought together some 40 scholars, theologians, writers and intellectuals from Asia, Europe, Africa, and the United States. The work of the Conference, according to its press release, was based on "the assumption that Cold War conceptions and policies derived from them have failed and have produced the disaster which Viet Nam is today. Therefore, the Conference sought alternative conceptions which might result in reasonable and constructive policies to achieve a peaceful and humane end to the war in Viet Nam."
The Conference divided into four Study Groups, each considering the problem of peace in Viet Nam from different aspects. One group considered the situation from the standpoint of international politics; the second, in terms of social and economic development; the third, in terms of conflict and conflict resolution; the fourth, from the standpoint of revolutionary warfare.
Although the Study Groups worked independently and developed a variety of recommendations, there was agreement among the participants on the following propositions. Again quoting from the press report of the conference
"that the bombing of North Viet Nam must cease
that there should be a general cease fire in South Viet Nam
that the settlement of the problem of Viet Nam must be considered as political, not military
that negotiations must include the National Liberation Front in its own right as a principal party to the conflict in South Viet Nam
that peace and stability in Asia require the admission of the People's Republic of China to the United Nations
that there should be a fundamental reassessment of the goals and methods of United States foreign policy."
The record group consists of two series, Conference Papers and Sound recordings of the speeches and study group sessions at the conference. The papers series includes correspondence, minutes, papers read at the conference, and other administrative files. Correspondents (to and from) include:
Hannah Arendt, Sept. 17, 1965
Germaine Brée, Aug. 3, 1965, Aug. 9, 1965, Sept. 25, 1965, Oct. 11, 1965
J. Daniel Burke
J. Edgar Edwards
Jerome D. Frank, Sept. 9, 1965
Erich Fromm, Sept. 4, 1965
Herbert Kelman
Martin Luther King, Jr., Aug. 26, 1965, Aug. 31, 1965, Sept. 8, 1965, Sept. 17, 1965
Archibald MacLeish, Aug. 5, 1965, Aug. 13, 1965
Emil Mazey, Aug. 30, 1965, Sept. 7, 1965
Arthur Miller, Aug. 27, 1965, Sept. 30, 1965
Mary C. Wright, June 7, 1965, July 28, 1965, Sept. 5, 1965.
The sound recordings include speeches by Arthur Miller, Edwin T. Dahlberg, Lord Fenner Brockway, Makoto Oda, and Emil Mazey, among others.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Congresses.Congresses.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Women and peace.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Intellectual life.; University of Michigan--Congresses.Congresses.; Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.
Contributors - Sound Recordings:
Kelman, Herbert C.; Mazey, Emil, 1913-1983; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.
Contributors - Papers:
Arendt, Hannah.; Brée, Germaine.; Burke, Joseph Daniel.; Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.; Frank, Jerome D. (Jerome David), 1909-2005.; Fromm, Erich, 1900-1980.; Kelman, Herbert C.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Mazey, Emil, 1913-1983; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.; Wright, Mary Clabaugh.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Conference papers, 1965
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Papers read at the conference, 1965; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Prospectus (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Schedules, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and press releases, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Lists, 1965 (Box 1)
- Sound recordings: reel-to-reel tapes
  [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam Plenary session: Welcomes and keynote addresses, 1965 September 14; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3 ¾ ips
    - [Part 1-1], [851510-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Welcome and keynote address at Rackham Lecture Hall; 9-12 AM.)
    - [Part 2], [851510-SR-1-2]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965;Welcome and keynote address at Rackham Lecture Hall)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam Study Group #2: P.M. Session, 1965 September 14; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3 ¾ ips
    - [Part 1-1], [851510-SR-2-1-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Study Group 2. (tape no. 2, track no.1).)
    - [Part 1-2], [851510-SR-2-1-2]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; (tape no. 2, track no.2).)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam Study Group #2: A.M. Session, 1965 September 15; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3 ¾ ips
    - [Part 1-1], [851510-SR-3-1-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965;(tape no. 3, track no. 1); A portion of this tape is in French.)
    - [Part 1-2], [851510-SR-3-1-2]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; (tape no. 3, track no. 2).)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam Study Group #2: P.M. Session, 1965 September 15; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3 ¾ ips
    - [Part 1-1], [851510-SR-4-1-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; (tape no. 4, track no. 1).)
    - [Part 1-2], [851510-SR-4-1-2]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; (tape no. 4, track no. 2).)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam Study Group #2: A.M. Session, 1965 September 16; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3 ¾ ips
    - [Part 1-1], [851510-SR-5-1-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; (tape no. 5, track no. 1).)
    - [Part 1-2], [851510-SR-5-1-2]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; (tape no. 5, track no. 2).)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-6-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 1; DeWitt Baldwin speech; Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. letter is read; Daniel Burke, moderator, reads Joint Statement; Report of Study Group 1: Windmiller; Study Group 2: Douglas F. Dowd.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-7-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 2; Study Group 2: Douglas F. Dowd; Study Group 3: Morton Deutsch; Study Group 4: Eqbal Ahmad.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-8-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 3; Study Group: Eqbal Ahmad; Study Group 4-Jean Lacouture; Ahmad gives brief translation of Lacouture presentation; Portions of this speech are in French.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-9-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 4; Daniel Burke announcements; Albert Chammah introduces Ernest Winter, speech; Mohammed Lahbabi, speech.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-10-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 5; Mohammed Lahbabi speech (cont.); Edwin T. Dahlberg, speech.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-11-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 6; Edwin T. Dahlberg, speech (cont.); Robert Parris, speech; Daniel Burke adjourns the afternoon session.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-12-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 7; Marshall D. Sahlins introduction; Lord Fenner Brockway speech.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-13-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 8; Marshall D. Sahlins introduction; Makoto Oda speech.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-14-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 9; Makoto Oda, speech (cont.); Marshall D. Sahlins introduction; Emil Mazey speech; Arthur Miller speech.)
  - Alternative Solutions for Vietnam; Sessions, 1965 September 17; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851510-SR-15-1]; mp3 file; (International Conference on Vietnam September 14 to 17, 1965; Part 10; Arthur Miller speech (cont.); Marshall D. Sahlins adjourns session.)